A Guide to the Office of the President: G. Tyler Miller Papers, 1941-1998: UA 0025
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Office of the President: G. Tyler Miller Papers
1941-1998
Special Collections, James Madison University
Miller, G. Tyler (George Tyler), 1902 – 1988
Burch, Donna
JMU Office of the President
UA 0025
3.2 cubic feet; 8 boxes
The Office of the President: G. Tyler Miller Papers are comprised of interviews, correspondence, minutes, reports, court documents and judiciary transcripts created during Miller's tenure as president of Madison College from 1949-1971. The collection is comprised of three series: Professional Papers, Court Documents, and Disciplinary Papers.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research with the exception of Series 3: Disciplinary Papers, which is closed due to FERPA restrictions. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection consists of several accessions: documents from the Office of the President on January 1, 1996; files from the Chancellor's Office (President Emeritus, Ronald Carrier) February 17, 2004.
Bio/Historical Note
George Tyler Miller was born July 25, 1902 in Washington, Virginia. He earned a B.S. from Virginia Military Academy in 1923. He was the third president of Madison College, serving from 1949-1971. During his administration, enrollment increased from 1,000 students to 4,300. The campus was enlarged by 240 acres, and twenty-one major buildings were constructed during his tenure. During his tenure, he served as director of the National Commission on Accreditation and President of the American Association of State Colleges and Universities. President Miller died in 1988.
Scope and Content
The G. Tyler Miller Papers are comprised of interviews, correspondence, minutes, reports, court documents and judiciary transcripts created during Miller's tenure as president of Madison College from 1949-1971. The collection is comprised of three series: Professional Papers, Court Documents, and Disciplinary Papers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series, and are arranged by subject matter and chronology.
Series 1: Professional Papers, 1940-1983
Series 2: Court Documents, 1969-1998 (bulk 1969-1971)
Series 3: Disciplinary Papers, 1965-1971 (Restricted)
Related Materials
Events leading to strike of 1970, Box 1: Folder 10, JMU Student Government Association Records, UA 0007, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA. https://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/manuscripts/0007sga.aspx.
Jay G. Rainey Papers, 1970-1996, bulk 1970-1977, SC 0024, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA. https://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/manuscripts/SC0024Rainey.aspx
Rainey, Jay. Oral History Interview by Jeremy Turner, 1998. SdArch 11-2., Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA. http://catalog.lib.jmu.edu/record=b1626325
Bibliography
Dingledine, Raymond C. "Madison College, the First Fifty Years, 1908-1958." Harrisonburg, VA: Madison College, 1959.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Miller, G. Tyler (George Tyler), 1902-1988; Madison College -- History; James Madison University -- History; Education, Higher -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- History; Universities and colleges -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- History; Madison College -- Presidents; Education, Higher -- Administration
Genre and Form Terms:
Minutes (administrative records); Letters (correspondence); Administrative reports; Legal documents; Newspaper clippings
- 1: Professional Papers, 1941-1998
  Scope and Content
  Series 1. Professional Papers, 1941-1998, chiefly contains correspondence, reports. It is arranged by subject, which is how the files were organized at the time of reprocessing.
  The Virginia Council on Higher Education files are comprised of correspondences and reports. The bulk of the correspondences are between President Miller and Paul Farrier, Executive Secretary of the State Council of Higher Education until 1957, and subsequently, with William Hugh McFarlane Director of the State Council of Higher Education. Interfiled with the correspondence are reports, studies, questionnaires, other forms that pertained to Virginia Council matters. Some topics covered are: capital outlay requests, coeducation, enrollment and admission policy, dining facilities, budgets, salaries, campus visit by members of the state Council of Higher Education, scholarships, space utilization studies and questionnaires, teacher supply studies, and educational television.
  The Virginia Presidents' Council of State Aided Institutions files contain correspondence between Miller and other presidents and administrative staff of Virginia colleges and universities. Topics include a cost study of state-supported institutions of higher learning, and a committee to study admission problems of state-supported institutions of higher learning, and a budget proposal for the state. The 1963 file includes correspondences, agendas, meeting minutes, and a 1963 issue of "The School Administrator." It also contains several reports: The Council of Presidents Economic Development Report (1963), Statement of the Council of Presidents State-Aided Institutions of Higher Learning in Virginia to the Commission on State and Local Revenues and Expenditures and Related Matters (1963), Higher Education and Economic Development in Virginia" report, a report on "admission problems" (1963), and faculty salary guides. Other items include a report called "Virginia's Crisis in Higher Education," a budget and capital outlay questionnaire regarding instructional maintenance and operations budget, invoices, correspondence with L.M. Kuhn of the State Governor's budget office, and Association of University Professor report on Academic Salary data and compensation indices for 1964-1965.
  The Virginia Board of Education files, 1950-1964, are largely comprised of correspondence with state officials. Topics include preparations for a visit with Virginia governor, John S. Battle, to contest state budget appropriations; the admittance of men students and coeducation; proposed graduate programs (1954); and the naming of buildings. A 1954 report of local public school divisions in Virginia; Elementary School Principals conference (1954). Also included here are reports and correspondence with J.L, Blair Buck, Coordinator of Teacher education; Nannie Mae M. Williams, Assistant Supervisor of Teacher Education; J.H. Bradford, Director of the Budget; Senator Robert Button; Thomas T. Hamilton, Associate Director of Instruction; Dowell J. Howard, Superintendent of Public Instruction; Alfred L. Wingo, Supervisor of Research; Dr. Woodrow Wilkerson, Supervisor of Secondary Education; Llyod S. Myer, State Records Administrator; Rosa H. Loving, State Supervisor Home economics Education; Percy H. Warren, Madison College Academic Dean; Leonard G. Muse; and Senator Robert Button.
  The Civil Defense files contain correspondence, questionnaires and reports documenting how Madison College dealt with defense strategies during the Cold War. Files includes blueprints of many Madison College buildings on campus, and the use of other Harrisonburg buildings, such as Rockingham Memorial Hospital, as bomb shelter sites.
  The folder, "Biographical sketches of Miller Presidency" contains reminiscences of Miller's secretary Carolyn Caracofe Rabunsky; memorial services that were held in 1988 after President Miller's death; and Paul C. Cline's article, "Madison College in the 1960s."
  - G. Tyler Miller Inauguration Papers, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - G. Tyler Miller Inauguration Recording, December 10, 1949
    - Original phonodisc records, December 10, 1942 (Box OV1)
    - Preservation master, December 10, 1942 (Box 1, Cd-r UA0025-OP-002)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Council of Higher Education, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Presidents' Council of State Aided Institutions, 1956, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Presidents' Council of State Aided Institutions, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Presidents' Council of State Aided Institutions, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Board of Higher Education, Director of Personnel, 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - State Legislation Affecting Madison College, 1941-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - US Office of Education, 1947-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fire Insurance Report on Madison College buildings, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fire Insurance Report on Madison College buildings, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Civil Defense Planning at Madison College, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Civil Defense Planning at Madison College, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Madison Day, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Architects regarding Burruss Science Hall, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General Education Program Report, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Proposed Chapel, 1954-1962, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National Education Association, 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Pupil Placement Board, 1958-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Percy Warren, 1962-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence regarding Retirement, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - G. Tyler Miller interviewed by Raymond Dingledine and Martha Caldwell, July 14, 1982
    - Transcript and supporting documents, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Original audiocassette, July 14, 1982 (Box 1, Audiocassette UA0025-CS-001)
    - Preservation master, July 14, 1982 (Box 1, Audiocassette UA0025-CS-002)
  - Reflections on Miller Presidency, 1982-1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- 2: Court Documents, 1964-1998 (bulk 1969-1971) 1969-1971
  Series 2: Court Documents, 1964-1998 (bulk 1969-1971), is comprised of documents related to a lawsuit filed by Madison College student, Jay Rainey against G. Tyler Miller and members of the Board of Visitors in 1969, as well as a lawsuit filed by Madison College student Lewis Sword against Dean of Madison College, James Fox. The series includes newspaper clippings regarding the court proceedings and protests conducted on campus from 1969-1970, memos and press releases from the administration, and correspondence.
  - Jay Rainey et. al. v. G. Tyler Miller et. al (No. 69-C-H-6) Court Documents, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Jay Rainey et. al. v. G. Tyler Miller et. al (No. 69-C-H-6) Depositions, October 19, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Jay Rainey et. al. v. G. Tyler Miller et. al (No. 69-C-H-6) Depositions, October 27, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Lewis Sword et. al. v. James Fox et. al. (No. 282-70-R) Court Documents, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lewis Sword et. al. v. James Fox et. al. (No. 70-C-26-H) Court Documents, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clipping Photocopies, 1964-1970, 1977, 1998, 1964-1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum regarding protests, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Trial Procedure for Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- 3: Disciplinary Papers, 1964-1971
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted
  Series 3: Disciplinary Papers, 1965-1971 is closed due to FERPA restrictions. It is comprised of documents that chronicle the disciplinary proceedings of students charged with various infractions, with the bulk of the materials related to a protest at Wilson Hall in 1969 that resulted in the arrests of students and faculty. The Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearings were conducted in a trial style and transcribed by court stenographer, Lane's Court Reporters, of Charlottesville Virginia.
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, May 12, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, May 12, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, May 13, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 1, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 1, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 1, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 2, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 2, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 2, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 3, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 3, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 4, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearing Transcript, June 4, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - G. Tyler Miller File Labelled, "Jay Rainey", 1965-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Excerpts of Minutes from Board of Visitors Meetings, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Attorneys, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Re: Faculty Judiciary Committee Hearings, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of the Faculty Judiciary Committee, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)